Novik, Morris. Papers. 6036/032
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Novik, Morris. Papers
1931-1985
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Novik, Morris
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
6036/032
2.11 cubic feet
2.11111111111111 linear ft.
Articles, reprints, pamphlets, correspondence, photographs.
This collection consists of records documenting Morris Novik's work as Broadcast Consultant for the ILGWU, especially relating to the union's political campaign programs. Also included are some materials relating to the ILGWU's Unity House.
5770060
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, October 02, 2011
EAD encoding:
Kathryn Dowgiewicz, January 10, 2013
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States, the ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. In 1995, the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE).
Biographical / Historical
Morris S. Novik was born in Nevel, Russia on November 15, 1903. He emigrated with his family to the U.S. as a young boy and settled in the Lower East Side of Manhattan. He joined the Young People's Socialist League in 1918, becoming chairman from 1921-1924. Novik joined the staff of the ILGWU and was the director of Unity House (1927-1932), the union vacation resort in the Poconos. After launching the Discussion Guild which presented lectures and debates with leading scholars, he was director from 1925-1932. In 1932 Novik was hired at WEVD and instituted programming that included lectures, debates and discussions about politics and socialist and labor issues. His success and innovation led to Novik becoming the director of WNYC, the New York City Municipal Broadcasting System, during the administration of Mayor Fiorello H. La Guardia from 1938-1945. Due to Novik's socialist and labor background, the station was investigated for alleged Soviet and Communist propaganda. But, he continued to improve the reputation of WNYC by adding programming including classical music, work by American composers, plays about African-Americans, and shows focusing on the American life and family. Winning numerous honors, the station received a Peabody Award for public service in 1945.
Beginning in 1945, Novik was a Broadcast Consultant for the UAW, the AFL, and the ILGWU. He later started, bought and operated numerous radio stations including WLIB. Novik died in November 1996 days before his 93rd birthday.
Scope and Contents
The majority of the collection focuses on records from the ILGWU erected and managed FM radio stations around the countrythe Unity Broadcasting Corporation, of which Morris Novik worked as a consultant. Contained in the records are general correspondence, newspaper clippings and articles about union owned radio stations, and information from various markets and stations in different states. There is also much material on the shows and talent, transcripts from broadcasts, programming schedules, and clippings and publicity for the stations owned by the ILGWU and the shows aired and produced. Specific programming events such as the 1953 television broadcast of the film "With These Hands," the 1958 dressmakers' general strike, and the gala celebration and concert at Madison Square Garden honoring twenty five years of David Dubinsky's presidency include correspondence, publicity and marketing material, and information on the broadcasts in which the union utilized their radio stations for these events.
The bulk of the materials center on the use of the media for political purposes. Included is information from networks and the government, laws and regulations, and procedures regarding the issues of broadcasting political programs, including paid political programs. The ILGWU was very active in sponsoring and promoting political campaigns and began to employ the media by buying air time to endorse candidates. There is correspondence, programming and transcripts for broadcasts for the Truman, Kennedy, Johnson and Humphrey political campaign committees. Other various items pertaining to political broadcasts contain complete transcripts for programs that included celebrities and actors such as Tallulah Bankhead, Janet Leigh, and Henry Fonda, as well as the correspondence and invitations for the individuals from Hollywood and Broadway to appear on the ILGWU sponsored programs in conjunction with the politicians.
Another component of the collection includes documents on the ILGWU's Unity House, as Novik was the director of the resort. Featured are programs with menus for weekend and holiday events and themed dinner parties, pamphlets and brochures, information on theater and plays performed at Unity House, and a collection of clippings from the Jewish Daily Forward advertising Unity House and activities, mainly in Yiddish. Also contained is printed material from conventions including programs, proposed amendments, and resolutions.
Oversize posters include: The ILGWU 1968 Campaign Committee Humphrey Election poster, WFDR FM poster advertising shows for Marquis Childs and Joseph C. Harsch, "With These Hands" poster advertising the television broadcast, and the 1960, 1964 and 1968 Election on Coast-to-Coast Radio posters advertising ILGWU political programs with speakers including Adlai Stevenson, George Meany, Eleanor Roosevelt, Lyndon Johnson, John Kennedy, Huber Humphrey, Harry Truman and the stars of Hollywood and Broadway.
A complimentary collection of the papers of Morris S. Novik can also be found at the George Meany Archives.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/122: ILGWU. Unity House records 5780/005: ILGWU. Frederick F. Umhey correspondence
Unity House -- Archives.; Young People's Socialist League -- Archives.; New York (N.Y.). Municipal Broadcasting System -- Archives.; Novik, Morris S., -- 1903-; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union -- Archives.
5770060
- Unity House, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Unity House, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Unity Broadcasting Corporation, 1944-1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Local 89 against Massachusetts Broadcasting Company, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- ILGWU Education Department, "How can mass media more effectively serve the nation?", 1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Unity Corporation of Pennsylvania, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Unity Broadcasting Corporation of Massachusetts, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Unity Broadcasting Corporation, 1948-1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Unity Broadcasting Corporation of Missouri, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Promotion folder for Washington Report, WFDR (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Scope and Contents
  Oversize items moved to box 3.
- Political, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- ILG Campaign, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- ILG Campaign, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- ILG broadcasts, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Liberal Party, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Radio, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Union Health Center, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- With These Hands, television showings, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- With These Hands, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- ILGWU, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Includes With These Hands; oversize items moved to box 3.
- ILGWU, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Includes material on cooperative housing
- Frederick Umhey, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Mark Starr, 1955-1962 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Politics, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- ILG Campaign, radio programs, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- ILG Campaign, radio programs, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Madison Square Garden, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  June 13.
- Dressmakers strike, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Garment center rally, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- ILG broadcasts, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- ILG broadcasts, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- ILG broadcasts, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Civil rights, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Politics, scripts, radio series, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Politics, scripts, radio series, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Ralph Yarborough, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- ILGWU broadcast, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  October 7.
- ILGWU broadcast, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  October 14.
- Madison Square Garden rally, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  October 15.
- ILGWU broadcast, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  October 21.
- ILGWU broadcast, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  October 28.
- Garment center rally, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  October 29.
- Harry S. Truman and Harry Golden speech, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  November 2.
- NBC Political Broadcast Manual and FCC telegram, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- ILGWU series, miscellaneous, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Campaign cut-ins, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Apparel luncheon, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- ILGWU publicity, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- ILGWU radio series, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Furman and Gotham bills, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Campaign clippings, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- ILGWU broadcast, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  October 17.
- ILGWU broadcast, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  October 24.
- Garment center rally, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  October 30.
- ILGWU broadcast, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  October 31; oversize items moved to box 3.
- COPE, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- COPE, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- ILGWU, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- ILGWU, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- ILGWU broadcast, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  October 10.
- Politics, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Miscellaneous, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Liberal Party, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Publicity, 1939-1950 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Clippings, 1940-1959 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Publicity, 1940-1961 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Golden Jubilee Convention stationary, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Printed material, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Publicity, 1950-1982 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- ILGWU Archives, 1952-1985 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Posters, 1954-1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Includes posters for ILGWU Campaign and With These Hands.